Today's דף daf is קכ"ג, Kuf Chaf Gimmel, 123,
and I'm sorry, okay, and we begin with the very bottom of
קכ"ב עמוד ב', Kuf Chaf Bais Amud Bais, the two dots about
eight lines from the bottom, הקרום שאיבדן. Hakrum she'ibdan. So we're talking
about the type, various types of animals that skin is considered distinct
from the meat in the sense that it's not normally eaten and
therefore it doesn't have status of food, doesn't have status of meat
for laws of נבילה neveila and טומאת אוכלין, tumas ochlin, and we
pick up here with the point of the משנה mishna that if
you take the skins that are considered to be part of the
meat, like skins of lizards and various other animals that are considered
like meat-like or chickens, for example, but you tan them to make
them into a type of a leather or a parchment or whatever,
then they obviously are no longer considered to be like meat. So
the גמרא gemara says the so it says if you tan them,
you know, you work them or you walk on them, which is
a way of processing the leather. So the גמרא gemara says הילך
אין לא הילך לא, hilach in lo hilach lo, only if you
walked on it, presumably if you did not walk on it it
does not yet have that, you know, it does not yet change
status. והתני רבי חייא, Vehatani Rabbi Chiya, does not רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya teach אוזן חמור שתלאה לקופתו טהורה, ozen chamor shetlaha lekupato tehora,
if you take the the the the ear of a donkey that
seems to me that that's like a phrase somewhere, isn't it? Or
maybe that's an ear of a of a pig. Anyway, the ear
of a donkey that you then that you somehow use that leather
and you you laid it out as a mat for your box,
so you basically used it as a type of a covering for
your box, then it is טהור. tahor. It is even if it
was it is no longer considered like meat and is and therefore
it no longer can receive טומאה. tumah. Okay, so because you did
that very specific act that you turned it into a type of
a of a cover and you used it in that capacity. So
the גמרא gemara says so it seems like you have to actually
use it in a particular capacity, not just processing it. So the
גמרא gemara says here's the difference. תלאה אף על גב דלא הילך,
tlaha af al gav delo hilach, לא תלאה הילך אין לא הילך
לא. lo tlaha hilach in lo hilach lo. It depends. If you
use it in a capacity, you actually, like, you know, spread it
out over your box, then even if you did not walk on
it, but once you're using it in that way, that gives it
takes it out of the status of meat. Or if you processed
it and walked on it even if you have not yet used
it, either one would be enough. You process it or begin to
use it in that way, then it is not yet considered then
it stops being meat. And even though leather, by the way, can
become טמא, tamei, that's only if it's made into some type of
a receptacle, in these cases it would not. So now the גמרא
gemara says כמה כדי עיבוד, kama kedei ibud, how much do you
have to walk on something in order to make it considered like
it's been processed and it stops being meat and it's considered like
a type of a leather, this skin? So רב הונא אמר רב
ינאי, Rav Huna amar Rav Yannai, ארבע מילין, arba milin, four מיל.
mil. Four מיל mil is about a מיל mil it takes about
18 minutes to walk a מיל, mil, so four מיל mil is
about the time it takes to walk 72 minutes. So 72 minutes
worth of walking, it doesn't mean that the piece of leather has
to be four מיל mil long, but 72 minutes worth of walking
on this leather, that would be considered that it's been processed and
it's no longer sort of meat, it's leather. And now that leads
to an interesting digression about this idea of four מיל. mil. So
let's take a look. The side it has אמר רבי אבהו amar
Rabbi Abbahu as opposed to אמר רבי אבהו משום ריש לקיש, amar
Rabbi Abbahu mishum Resh Lakish, slightly different way of phrasing it. אמר
רבי אבהו אמר ריש לקיש, amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Resh Lakish, same
basic point, says the following about four מיל. mil. לגבל, legabel, to
knead dough, I'll explain what this means in a minute, לתפילה ולנטילת
ידים, litfilla u'lintilat yadayim, and for prayer and for washing hands, ארבע
מילין, arba milin, it's four מיל. mil. Now what does that mean?
So רש"י Rashi says it means that if you're it's a בעל
הבית baal habayis has hired you to knead dough for him, but
he wants you to do it בטהרה, betahara, right? It's somebody who
ate his חולין בטהרה, chullin betahara, let's say, in order to wash
your hands in order to be able to do it בטהרה, betahara,
you have to walk a very long distance or not wash your
hands, excuse me, wash the vessels that you're going to use, you
have to walk a very long distance. So there we say that
if he has to walk more than four מיל, mil, you're not
required to do it. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains it. תוספות
Tosafos doesn't like that because the other contexts in this גמרא gemara
make it first of all, it's funny if he hired you to
do a job, then that you could go ahead and do the
food בטומאה betuma would be a little bit funny even if it
is a big טירחא. tircha. But anyway, תוספות Tosafos doesn't like it
because the other examples here are talking about somebody that's going on
a journey. So he doesn't see that that's a reasonable description that
you're going on a journey and it's a question about doing your
חולין בטהרה. chullin betahara. So תוספות Tosafos says that so תוספות's Tosafos
alternate explanation is let me let me just check that.
Right, he explains it that you are going on a journey, it
has nothing to do with a worker, you're going on a journey
and you normally eat your bread בטהרה, betahara, you don't like it
to be done, you know, as which we know is a practice,
and you can get that type of bread if you keep on
going for another four מיל. mil. Right now, you know, this is
a very important issue, right, you know, you're driving on the highway,
you know, when you make your next stop for the rest stop,
how long do you keep things off until you go ahead, and
we're going to actually see a much more common scenario in a
minute when we get into נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. So here's the
point is you would like to eat your חולין בטהרה. chulin betaharah.
You if you can wait up to four, so if it's within
four מיל, mil, then you then you should wait. If it's more
than four מיל, mil, then don't bother with it, you know, don't
bother eating your חולין בטהרה chulin betaharah this time if you have
to, if it's going to be that much more till you can
get to it. That's the case of לגבי דם. legabi dam. Now
תפילה tfilah is an interesting debate. רש"י Rashi says תפילה tfilah means
that in terms of a מנין, minyan, I want to דאוון daven
now, but I know that if I keep on going in another
four מיל, mil, I'll be able to get to a שול, shul,
and actually רש"י Rashi just mentions שול. shul. תוספות Tosafot says it
doesn't mean the שול shul per se, it means a מנין. minyan.
I know I'll be able to דאוון daven with a מנין. minyan.
So therefore in that case, I should keep on waiting in my
journey, not דאוון daven now, wait till I get that place where
I'm going that will have actually a שול shul and will enable
me to דאוון daven with a מנין. minyan. That's interesting because it
raises questions about what is the degree of a personal obligation to
דאוון daven with a מנין. minyan. מנין minyan is more of an
obligation on the ציבור tzibur than on the individual, but nevertheless, this
might not be so to speak speaking here about a strict obligation
as much as what's ideal. It's more ideal that you wait, if
you can wait, if you can get a מנין minyan within four
מיל, mil, then wait. If it's going to be even much longer
till you get a מנין, minyan, then you can go ahead and
דאוון daven now. But again, talking about what would be preferable and
ideal. That's how תוספות Tosafot explains it. More I would say relevant
להלכה, lehalacha, the way this is explained is if you want to,
if you need to wash your hands before דאוונינג, davening, and that
ties into the next idea of נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. And it
ties into the question of available water, which seems to be the
more sort of common theme here about available water, right? Because if
you want to also the case of חולין בטהרה chulin betaharah is
that you want a מקוה mikveh in order to make things טהור.
tahor. So that way of explaining it is you have to דאוון,
daven,
you should wash your hands before you דאוון, daven, but it's going
to take more than four מיל mil before you get water. Do
you have to, what should you do? So if you can, if
within four מיל mil you can get water, wait till you get
the water before you wash your hands and דאוון. daven. If, however,
the water, if, however, it's more than that amount, then you don't
have to wash your hands, you can clean your hands on something
else, on wood, on stone, or whatever, you clean your hands without
using water and you דאוון daven then. That's תפילה. tfilah. And נטילת
ידים netilat yadayim is perhaps the most relevant. The נטילת ידים netilat
yadayim is, and this happens all the time, you're, you know, you're
on a car trip, you packed sandwiches, and you're hungry, you want
to eat while you're driving, but you don't have water. What do
you do? Do you do נטילת ידים, netilat yadayim, can you, can
you eat the sandwiches without doing נטילת ידים? netilat yadayim? And here
it says that if you can do it within four מיל, mil,
then you wait till you get that water and you do נטילת
ידים. netilat yadayim. If, however, it's going to be more than four
מיל, mil, you don't have to wait for the water. And what
do you do? You eat the sandwiches, let's say wrapped up in,
you know, in paper, so you're not touching the bread, but then
you can actually forgo the נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim. Now, if you
remember when we learned נטילת ידים, netilat yadayim, we learned that wrapping
was not a solution, that even if you wrap it, you have
to wash your hands. But in this circumstance, where there's not easily
available water and it means waiting more than four מיל, mil, they
actually allowed you not to wash your hands. A very relevant הלכה,
halacha, stuff that happens all the time when you are traveling. The
interesting question is how do you measure four מיל? mil? Because four
מיל, mil, as I said, if you're walking takes seventy-two minutes. If
you're on donkey, it takes less. If you're driving, takes a lot
less, right? If you're driving, four מיל mil might be four minutes.
So the question is, you know, is it real, so would I
really translate it as distance? And if water is any more than
four minutes away, I don't have to do it? It's a classic
case. Next rest stop, thirty-two miles, right? Do I have to wait
for thirty-two miles to get to the rest stop so I can
do נטילת ידים netilat yadayim so that I can have my sandwich,
or can I just eat the sandwich in the car? Do you
translate the four מיל mil here as time or as distance? It's
a very relevant שאלה. sheilah. It would seem to me פשוט pashut
it should be translated as distance. Because the question for you, I
mean not distance, as time. The question for you is not how
far you have to go, but how long you have to wait.
And how much, you know, so therefore it would seem to me
that that's how it should be measured. And if you can get
to a rest stop within an hour, you should wait to get
to the rest stop. More than that, like seventy-two minutes or whatever,
that then is go ahead and eat the sandwich, just don't touch
the bread.
You see that as a discussion? I mean, we didn't have cars,
but they did have...
Right, they did have donkeys. Yeah. So, I haven't had a chance
to look at it in depth. It's always been to me פשוט
pashut that it should be measured in terms of time, but I
know I assume it's discussed in the פוסקים. poskim. I haven't had
a chance to look into it. Okay. So anyway, since we mentioned
four מיל, mil, we mentioned all these three things, which again, it's
easier to understand all of them as a question about water is
not immediately available. So you have to do stuff בטהרה. betaharah. You
have to wash your hands. You have to for דאוונינג. davening. You
have to wash your hands for bread. If it's within four מיל,
mil, wait. If it's longer than four מיל, mil, then forgo it,
find an alternative. Okay, wipe your hands on something clean, wrap the,
if it's for דאוונינג, davening, wrap the bread,
etc., etc. Okay. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said, אי הכי.
I hachi. אמרה *amrah*, it wasn't רבי אבהו *Rebbe Avuhu*, it was
איבו *Evo*. Fine. וארבעה *V'arba* אמרי *amri*, and he said four things,
not three. אמרה *Amrah*, וחדא מנייהו *v'chada mineihu*, the other one is
עבודה *avodah* that the issue of our משנה Mishnah. *mishna* about working
the skin into into leather, that that needs to be walked on
for four מיל *mil*. So he added that to this list of
three things. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא לא שנו lo shanu, אלא
ella לפניו *Amar Rebbe Yose b'Rebbe Chanina lo shanu ela l'fanav*. And
this is also very relevant. This idea of waiting four מיל *mil*,
that's only if it's going to be coming up in your journey.
אבל לאחוריו *Aval l'achorav*, if you have to retrace your steps, אפילו
מיל אחד אינו חוזר *afilu mil echad eino chozer*. Even one מיל
*mil* you don't have to go back, which makes a lot of
sense. Because even though you could say you go back a מיל
*mil* and you come back, it's only the time of two מיל
*mil*. Sure, the time of two מיל *mil*, but you haven't advanced
in your journey, right? In one, it's a question about waiting, but
you're still getting closer to where you have to get. You're just
waiting to eat, or you're waiting to דאווען *daven*. In the other
case, you're actually going out of your way, you're losing time. So
there he says, even if it's just a מיל *mil* behind you,
you don't have to go back in order to do it. So
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, so רב Rav אחא בר יעקב אמר
*Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar*, ומנה *u'mina* from that we can infer
מיל הוא דאינו חוזר *mil hu d'eino chozer*. You don't have to
go back if it's a מיל *mil* behind you. הפחות ממיל חוזר
*Ha pachos mi'mil chozer*, less than that you do have to go
back. So that actually would be interesting. You just passed a rest
stop, right? And the next rest stop is, I don't know, is
80 miles. Sometimes you're on certain stretches of the highway, not normally,
depends on which highway. Next rest, last rest stop for the next
80 miles, right? So in that type of a case, maybe if
you could double back and go back to the rest stop and
it's within like 15 minutes or so, 18 minutes, you according to
this you would have to do it, rather than using this alternative
to eating bread without washing the hands.
So there you can't go back? What? With a like a thruway
you can't go back.
If you can't go backwards, then obviously that's not a relevant question.
Okay. תנו רבנן *Tano Rabbanan*, we taught, לגיון העובר ממקום למקום ונכנס
לבית הבית טמא tamei, *ligyon ha'over mi'makom l'makom v'nichnas l'bayis ha'bayis tamei*.
If a army troop is passing through various cities and enters into
a house, you have to assume that everything in the house is
טמא tamei *tamei*. Why? שאין לך כל לגיון ולגיון שאין לו קרקפלין
*she'ein lach kol ligyon v'ligyon she'ein lo karkapalin*. There is not any
army troop, I presumably you're talking about the Roman army, that does
not have some skulls among them. Apparently they would behead their foes
and carry skulls with them. ואל תתמה *V'al titma*, don't be astounded
by this. שהרי קרקפלו של רבי ישמעאל מונח בראש מלכים *she'harei karkapalo
shel Rebbe Yishmael munach b'rosh melachim*. There you go, like right out
of the יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* liturgy with the עשרה הרוגי מלכות
*Asara Harugei Malchus*, that רבי ישמעאל *Rebbe Yishmael*'s skull or his face
is there in the palace of kings, or the head of kings
literally, obviously evokes that whole idea about the flaying of the skin
off of his face. And presumably, now why is this mentioned here?
I mean, it is true we're talking about טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah
v'taharah*, but still, I mean, only very generally about what type of
things. But it seems because of this idea about the skin being
removed from the leather, and even in the משנה mishna. *mishna* we
had mentioned the skin of humans, making the skin of humans into
certain vessels. So it seems to that that's certainly a theme that
here is being picked up.
You accept that story as historical?
Apparently, you know, I mean, it sounds like it, right? It sounds
like it's not here as a מדרש *midrash*, it's in the הלכה
*halachic* context and referencing it. Yeah, I mean, at least at least
this משנה mishna, *mishna* of this ברייתא baraita. *braisa* did.
Okay. Now, next משנה mishna. *mishna*. So that is it, again with
that so ending up that idea about skin and the meat, but
again with that fascinating discussion about on a journey and waiting for
מיל *mil*, but if you can't but if it's more than four
מיל *mil*, certain alternatives to things like washing your hands for bread
and washing your hands for דאווענען *davening*.
Yes, two quick questions. You said to eat bread בטהרה *b'taharah*, meaning
washing the hands?
No, the first case of לגבל *l'gabel* was beyond just eating your
washing the hands which everybody's obligated. That was a subsection of people
that had a practice to eat all of their food בטהרה *b'taharah*,
which meant not only did they wash their hands, but all the
vessels used were brought into the מקווה mikvah, *mikvah* beforehand, went even
in the making of it, they were טהור tahor, *tahor*, not just
in the actual eating of it.
So they had to find a place where
they could immerse the vessels and exactly.
And the other one was did you say if the if the
next stop was 80 minutes you might have to go back 18
minutes?
Right. Well, the point is you don't have to wait more than
four מיל *mil*. So if it's more than four מיל *mil* in
front of you, you don't have to wait. But the end asked,
but if it's within a מיל *mil* behind you, you would have
to go back. So then you don't have this say, oh, I
don't have to wash my hands. No, because you could go back
for 10 minutes and that's therefore catch yeah. That's assuming we go
by time, which I'm taking for granted. Okay. Now we look at
the next משנה mishna *mishna*.
That's also assuming the post טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah v'taharah* world that
we're in or is that in the טהרה *taharah* world?
Yeah, I mean, no, post טומאה tumah *tumah*, the הלכה *halacha* of
washing hands, yeah. The לגבל *l'gabel* was a unique case, but the
washing of the hands is standard.
Okay. המפשיט בבהמה וחיה בטהורה ובטמאה bitehora uvitme'a, בדקה ובגסה Badakah uvagasah
*Hamafshit b'behemah v'chayah b'tahorah u'v'tmeiah b'dakah u'v'gasah*. Now we are once again,
haven't left that world about skin and meat and when is the
skin considered connected to the meat as a שומר shomer *shomer* or
as a יד yad? *yad*. So here you are, you are flaying
a בהמה *behemah* or a חיה *chayah* or a deer, whether it
is טהורה tehorah, או טמאה tmeia, *tahorah or tmeiah*, whether it is
a... kosher animal or a non-kosher animal, maybe it's a pig, okay?
It doesn't really matter. You want to use the skin, get some
good pig skin for a football, whatever it is, you want to
get some skin and the question is when is the skin connected
to the meat as a יד yad. or as a שומר shomer
to bring טומאה tumah to the meat or to communicate טומאה tumah
from the meat if the meat is a נבילה neveilah or it's
a non-kosher animal which is by
definition a נבילה. neveilah. בדקה ובגסה bedaka uvigasa, whether it's a small
animal like a sheep or a large one like a cow. לשטיח
Lishatiach if you are using the skin, your intention of using the
skin is in order to use it as a type of a
mat. You know, the, you know, like you always see in like
the, you know, like the Indians, like, you know, excuse me, the
American, Native Americans I should say, but you see it like in
the movies, you know, they have that big like animal skin as
like a floor mat. So if, and we mentioned it before, using
a piece of leather like as a cover or something like that.
So if you're planning on using the skin as a type of
a mat, then כדי אחיזה. kedei achizah. Once you have the amount
that you can grasp in your hand, we'll see what that is
in גמרא, Gemara you would think it's a טפח tefach because that's
the size of your hand, but according to the גמרא Gemara actually
it's two טפחים, tefachim, but the amount that you hold, so up
till that amount it is considered connected to the meat. Let's use
the גמרא Gemara page as an example. This is the leather, this
is the meat of the animal, I'm flaying the leather. So I'm
slowly peeling this off, right? So if up to a כדי אחיזה,
kedei achizah, the amount I can grasp, like here, you know, a
טפח tefach or two טפחים tefachim worth, it's still considered connected to
the meat and therefore if I touch this it's like touching the
meat, I become טמא, tamei. if something טמא tamei. touches this it's
like the meat becomes טמא. tamei, Once I've peeled away more than
the amount to hold and I touch this, it is not connected
to the meat even though obviously down here it's connected, but I've
peeled away more and therefore this touching this part does not communicate
טומאה tumah, to the meat or from the meat to me.
Is this the entirety of the skin that's been flayed or
just the part of the יד?
yad No, it's the process of flaying. No, I know, but as
I get now and I've crossed the threshold such that this over
here is now no longer connected.
Right. Well, it's no longer connected.
Right. So the part you're still considering connected. Right.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to stop, meaning I'm
peeling it away, right? I haven't even removed the piece. The part
that is one with the meat obviously is connected and if I
touch it then it communicates טומאה tumah both ways. This part is
not considered connected. Mordechai is asking what about the part that's right
next to the meat that's been removed but is still that first
like טפח tefach close to the meat? That's exactly what the גמרא
Gemara is going to discuss. Okay. So that's what it is if
I'm using it for a mat. We'll discuss why the uses matter
in a minute. Let's keep on going.
Now, ולחמת ulechemat if I'm planning on using it for a, for
a water skin, you know, a what do they call a canteen,
but not a canteen, a flask, but what do they call it
when it's made out of leather? A water skin I guess. Anyway,
עד שיפשיט את החזה ad sheyaphshit et hachazeh until I remove the
chest area. Why? Because presumably I am not in the leather business,
but presumably when I need to use the leather for a flask,
the way I have to remove it is by removing the whole
leather. Apparently,
and therefore meaning normally the way you would remove it is you
would slice the animal lengthwise by the chest and you'd peel away,
you know, from the middle of the chest. That was considered easier.
For some reason in order to get the quality, maybe even the
size, you know, you know, who knows, they went on long journeys
so maybe they didn't have just a personal flask, maybe a... That's
true. You don't want stitches. There you go. Oh, that's probably it.
So what you would have to, you would do when you wanted
a water, the leather for a water skin is you would peel
it from the feet to the head. So that you would probably,
Mordechai is right, you don't have as many, you want a whole
thing, no stitches and so on. That is much harder, takes a
lot more effort to remove it that way and until you get
to the chest area, the chest area is the hardest to remove
it from. After you pull it away all the way across through
the through the chest area, it's from the neck to the head
becomes is easy. So until you actually pull it away all the
way through the through the chest area, it's still considered connected and
any part you touch brings טומאה tumah. because it's a very hard
job and it's, you know, it's still considered one with the meat
until you get so far to peel it away from the chest.
המרגיע, Hamargia, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, the simple case is you're doing
it from the head to the feet. The next case is feet
to the head. So if you're doing from the head to the
feet until you get beyond the chest
area. המרגיע Hamargia from the word רגל, regel, if you start from
the feet and go up to the head, then
כולו חיבור לטומאה לטמא ולטמא, kulo chibur letumah letame uletame, then it's
all because basically you have to get
until you get beyond the chest you've done the whole thing. So
the point is the same. If you're removing it from head to
feet or feet to head, it's considered connected until you pass the
chest. But in the case of head to feet, head to feet
means that when you get about halfway then it's not considered connected
anymore. In the case of feet to head, you would have to
get beyond the chest is basically to finish the job, so it's
always considered connected. Now the remaining question is, well not really all,
what about the head area? So that's going to be discussed at
the end of the
משנה. mishna, עור שעל הצואר, Or she'al hatzavar, what about the neck
skin if you're going from the feet... to the head. Once you've
got beyond the chest, is that still considered connected or not? So
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri אומר omer אינו חיבור,
eino chibur, that is no longer considered connected once you've gotten that
far, וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim, חיבור chibur עד שיפשיט כולו. ad sheyafsheet
kulo. No, that is still on the skin. So even though it's
on it's about easy to pull off, basically you've got beyond the
chest, it's like two seconds to pull the rest of it off.
Okay, I'm exaggerating, I don't even know. But the point is, so
how the the skin on the neck, it literally is right on
the meat. But it's about to come off without any effort in
two seconds. Is that considered connected to the meat or not? And
that's the debate at the end of this משנה. mishna, Now, this
entire משנה, mishna. the question that of course I'm sure everybody is
dying to ask is, what way are we considering this halachically connected?
We know two principles, שומר shomer and יד. yad, שומר shomer. is
a protector, יד yad as a manipulator. There is no hint in
this משנה. mishna רש"י Rashi reads the cases to be about יד,
yad, a way to manipulate. But that's very strange. What does any
of this have to do with how easy it is to pull
off or how hard it is to what does that have to
do with whether you're still able to manipulate the meat by handling
the leather or not, by handling the skin or not? תוספות Tosafos
says, תוספות Tosafos tries to explain by רש"י Rashi how it makes
sense, but I'd rather just acknowledge that and bracket it. תוספות Tosafos
says what I think makes a lot more sense about this, that
it's a sense of שומר. shomer
Now normally, the idea of שומר shomer is that if you remember
that for שומר shomer to communicate טומאה, tumah, it protects the thing,
you have to touch directly opposite the meat. Right? יד yad works
at a distance, but שומר shomer, is directly on top of it.
Okay? So what תוספות Tosafos so here, yes, the skin is being
a שומר, shomer, but it's not directly connected to the meat. And
the question therefore is, maybe though if it is right next to
it and it's, you know, the remaining part of it is connected,
and this is a little flap that's unconnected, maybe that's still considered
to be connected. And that's what the משנה mishna. is talking about.
So, if you're pulling it away and it's an easy thing, then
the only part that's considered connected is the very beginning flap. Once
you start pulling away more, then it's no longer related, it's going
to be easily removed and so on. When you're doing it from
the feet to the head or the head to the feet, it's
much harder to remove it. As we said, the chest area is
very difficult. In that type of a case, what if it's still
very closely connected and it's going to require a lot of effort,
even if part of it is flapped over, it's still all considered
connected and therefore it still functions as a שומר, shomer, and if
you touch it, it's a way of communicating. So according to תוספות,
Tosafos, because we're in the principle category of שומר, shomer. which is
the idea of being one, not the category of יד, yad. which
is the idea of manipulating, the question of how intimately connected it
is and how easy or hard it is to remove is very
relevant to the question of whether the flap is considered to be
still connected to the meat. And you have an interesting case. At
the end of the משנה, mishna you have the case of the
head area where even though it is connected, because it's very easy
to come off, it's like it's already removed and it's like it's
not connected. And in the beginning of the משנה, mishna you have
the case that even though it's peeled, because it's hard to remove
and because the rest of it remains connected, it's like the peeled
part is itself still connected. But that's how תוספות Tosafos reads it,
which is I think very straightforward, whether it's still considered to be
connected or not. Okay, so now let's see how the גמרא Gemara.
deals with it. You have a question מרדכי?
Mordechai? Kind of an observation. There's certainly cases where there's certain skin
areas of skin that's bonded, what I guess the fat layer and
then to the flesh, where to peel that skin takes a lot
of effort, you sometimes even have to take a knife and flay
it, whereas other skin really just kind of sags, you know, floats
on the surface and it's totally unconnected and you can manipulate it
around and on the hawk it just kind of like sags
like a sheet settled over them. Very interesting. Having witnessed this or
done it?
Done it. Really? Yeah, for sure by the chickens that we've been
playing and things like that. Wow, very interesting. They'll just pop over
the legs, for example, but the chest area is the area, yeah,
by the pelvis and things like that are very firmly bonded.
There you go. Very nice. Good.
Okay, so you have to use a knife when you're actually doing
it or you just pull it?
So that's what I'm saying. Some areas are not even connected. You
could use if you make a cut, you know, like a square
on the thing and then turn it over, it'll flop off on
its own. It's not even really bonded at all. Other areas are
very firmly bonded and have like a very usually they have a
very thick fat layer underneath. In those areas, sometimes you actually even
have to take your knife and flay it.
Right. So the way רש"י Rashi describes, and this exactly explains the
chest area and why it's easier when you're pulling away from the
chest rather than trying to do the whole thing, is that when
you cut that incision down the length of the chest and you're
pulling, the initial one or two טפחים tefachs really do require like
the use of a knife, but once you get beyond that, then
you can just pull
it all off.
Right. There you go. So that's exactly why that first טפח tefach
is still considered connected, but once you get beyond that first one
or two טפחים, tefachs, then it's going to be easy to come
off and then it's no longer considered connected. Which that's so thank
you. Thank you for illustrating exactly the case of the משנה. Mishnah
So let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara מכאן ואילך מאי?
Mikan va'eilach mai? Now what happens beyond that? This This is exactly
the question Mordechai asked. You're peeling away from the center of the
chest. You've now peeled away a good amount, more than כדי אחיזה.
kedei achiza. What is the story? This stuff on the top isn't
connected? What's the story with the טפח tefach right next to the
meat? Maybe that's still connected or not? So and now we're hearing
from Mordechai that once you get that far, actually רש״י Rashi says
it more or less, but once you get that far, even the
stuff that's close to the meat is going to come off very,
very easily. So there's an argument to say that that is not
considered connected anymore. And that's exactly what רב Rav, said. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, טהור המופשט. tahor hamufshat. Everything that's been peeled away is
טהור, tahor, even the stuff that's very close to the meat once
you've made some good progress. רבי אסי אמר, Rabbi Assi amar, טפח
הסמוך לבשר טמא. tefach hasamuch labasar tamei. No, the טפח tefach that's
right near the meat is still considered connected and it is still
טמא. tamei It's only the stuff that's beyond that that has, you
know, the flap that extends beyond that that is not connected. מיתיבי,
Meitivei, I'll ask you on רב אסי'ס Rav Assi's position. המפשיט כשיעור
הזה, Hamafshit keshiur hazeh, מכאן ואילך. mikan va'eilech. So we have a
ברייתא. baraita. Once you pull away, flay away beyond that amount of
כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza, which is one or two טפחים, tefachim, הנוגע
במופשט טהור. hanogea bamufshat tahor. If you touch any part that has
been flayed away, you and the meat are טהור, tahor. meaning it
doesn't communicate טומאה tumah, in either direction. מאי לאו, Mai lav, even
בטפח הסמוך לבשר? betefach hasamuch labasar? If it says if you touch
any part that's pulled away, presumably it means even the טפח tefach
that is closest to the meat. The גמרא gemara says, לא, לבד
מטפח הסמוך לבשר. Lo, levad mitefach hasamuch labasar. No, we mean any
of the extended part that's pulled away, but still the טפח tefach
closest to the meat, that still would be a שומר. shomer.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. We have another ברייתא. baraita
ועור שכנגד הבשר טמא. Ve'or shekeneged habasar tamei. If
you touch the skin opposite the meat, then it does communicate טומאה.
tumah, So that sounds like only if it's directly opposite the meat.
So and it says, הא בטפח הסמוך לבשר טהור. Ha betefach hasamuch
labasar tahor. If it's not directly connected to the meat, it's just
the טפח tefach closest to the meat, it sounds like it's טהור.
tahor. So the גמרא gemara says, לא, תנא כל טפח הסמוך לבשר
עור שכנגד הבשר קרי ליה. Lo, tanna kol tefach hasamuch labasar or
shekeneged habasar kari lei. The author of this ברייתא baraita would consider
the טפח tefach closest to the meat like essentially connected to the
meat. So when it says if you touch the skin connected to
the meat it's טמא, tamei. it means including this טפח tefach which
is so close that it's like it is connected to the meat.
Again, that is a stretch. The simplest point of this משנה Mishnah?
makes it very clear. Anything that's been flayed is not connected, anything
that's still connected is connected. But still רב אסי Rav Assi is
still trying to argue that even when you've pulled back a lot,
the טפח tefach closest to the meat remains considered connected. Okay, תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. המפשיט בבהמה ובחיה בטהורה ובטמאה. Hamafshit
bibehema uvichaya bitehora uvitme'a. A תוספתא Tosefta that starts just like our
משנה. Mishnah, You are flaying whether an animal
or a deer, בטהורה ובטמאה, whether it's a cow or a pig,
בדקה ובגסה, a sheep or a cow, לשטיח, lishatiach, if it's for
a mat, כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza, then only the initial amount of
grasping is considered connected.
וטפח הסמוך לבשר טהור. Vetefach hasamuch labasar tahor. But the טפח tefach
presumably when you continue, the טפח tefach that's right near after you've
gone more than כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza, the טפח tefach that's right
near the meat is טהור. tahor? So it's exactly like רב, Rav
it says it explicitly. The
גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן בטפח ראשון. Hacha bemai askinan betefach
rishon. We're talking about the first טפח. tefach. What does that mean?
So what רש״י Rashi says it means is the following: is that
when you are pulling
away, so the first after this is your כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza,
after you do your כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza, the next טפח tefach
remains very hard to remove. And that רש״י Rashi says until
you get beyond that then it's easy to remove. Now of course,
okay, but if that were true, then it's more of a reason
that that first טפח tefach should be טמא tamei. if it's hard
to remove, right? How does that explain why this ברייתא braita, said
טהור? tahor So רש״י Rashi explains it his way, which is that
it has to do with יד and how easy it is to
manipulate. And רש״י Rashi says that when you're just starting, even this
first טפח, tefach, even after you've pulled away כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza,
this first טפח tefach is very hard to use to manipulate and
you need to use your knife and it's not a good skin
to hold on to to manipulate, so it doesn't function as a
יד. Anyway, it's hard to understand if the idea is like I
was trying to read it and תוספות Tosafot was trying to read
it, like I'm adopting, that it's about being closely connected. If anything,
that first טפח tefach is more of a reason to be טמא.
tamei. So תוספות Tosafot actually quotes a גרסא girsa of רבינו חננאל
Rabbeinu Chananel that says exactly that, that the גרסא girsa was טפח
הסמוך לבשר טמא, tefach hasamuch labasar tamei, that supported רב אסי. Rav
Assi. And then רב's Rav response is, no, I'm talking when you're
just starting, when it's the first טפח tefach after כדי אחיזה, kedei
achiza, then I admit is still considered connected because that, as we've
heard from Mordechai and from רש״י, Rashi, is very tightly connected, so
that is considered connected, that first bit beyond כדי אחיזה. kedei achiza.
But once you get beyond that first טפח, tefach, now everything is
טהור tahor because now it's all just going to fall off. Okay,
so the way רב Rav. explains it is, as you're pulling away,
the first כדי אחיזה kedei achiza is connected. Not only that, if
you go beyond... כדי אחיזה, kedei achizah, the next טפח tefach is
connected because it's still really a tightly, tightly bound, and that's connected,
connected. Once you get beyond that, then everything just comes off easily,
and then even the skin right next to the meat is going
to be טהור tahor. because it all will fall off easily. They
make a lot of sense. Let's take a look. תנא, tana, we
taught in a ברייתא, braita כמה כדי אחיזה, kama kedei achizah, how
much is כדי אחיזה? kedei achizah? טפח. tefach. Okay, one טפח's tefach
worth, which makes sense, the amount to hold on. So the גמרא
Gemara says, והתניא, ve-hatanya, don't we have another ברייתא braita that says
טפחיים? tefachyim? So the גמרא gemara
says, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, טפח כפול. tefach kaful. When we say
a טפח, tefach, we mean a double טפח. tefach. Now, of course
that's a little fuzzy. Why would we mean that? Someone explained that
this is exactly consistent with what we said before about רב. That
the כדי אחיזה kedei achizah is connected, which let's say means a
טפח, tefach, and the next טפח tefach is also considered, you know,
connected. The טפח tefach closest to the meat, not the top part,
but the טפח tefach closest to the meat. And then afterwards, everything
becomes טהור. tahor. So that's why one ברייתא says טפח tefach because
that is the כדי אחיזה, kedei achizah, but the next one says
two טפחים tefachim because even when you remove another טפח, tefach, that
טפח tefach closest remains connected. But beyond that, then everything, even right
up to the meat itself, becomes טהור. tahor, Okay, so now we've
got the idea. The idea is how tightly connected is it? And
the tighter it is connected and once it comes off very easily,
then it is not considered connected and it is not a שומר.
תנן התם. tnan hatam. Now we are going to sort of digress
a little bit and circle back. So let's take a look. טלית
שהתחיל בה לקרוע, כיון שנקרעה רובה, שוב אינו חיבור, וטהורה. Talit she-hitchil
bah likroa, kivan she-nikre’ah rubah, shuv eino chibur, u-tehorah. So you have
a טלית talit which is טמא. tamei? Now, you tear it. One
way, the normal way in which you make a כלי kli טהור,
tahor. is you dunk it in a מקווה, mikvah.
which you can do by vessels and people, not by foods. You
can dunk them in a מקווה. mikvah.
Now, cloth also.
Cloth if cloth is טמא. tamei Normally cloth by itself, I mean
depends, you know, under what circumstances cloth.
Yes, but cloth as a garment. Yes, yes, yes. Okay, so you
dunk it in a מקווה. mikvah, Now, the alternative is you destroy
it. If you destroy it, it loses its identity and it becomes
טהור. tahor. So if you break a כלי חרס, kli cheres, what
does the תורה Torah say to do by כלי חרס? kli cheres?
ישבר. yishaver. So, I mean, actually,
so, I mean, although it says that also by whatever, by כשרות
kashrut issues. Anyway, but if you break it, it loses its identity
and it becomes טהור. tahor? Now, so if you tear this טלית,
talit, you didn't put it in a מקווה, mikvah you tear it.
At what stage does it stop being considered a טלית talit and
does it become טהור? tahor. So it says, כיון שהתחיל בה לקרוע,
כיון שנקרעה רובה, kivan she-hitchil bah likroa, kivan she-nikre’ah rubah, once you
get to the majority, שוב אינו חיבור, shuv eino chibur, it's not
like it's connected to itself anymore, right? And therefore טהורה, meaning less
than that, even though you wouldn't wear it with a half-torn טלית,
talit, but you might sew it up. So it's still all considered
one unit. But once you get beyond half, it's now not considered
one unit anymore, it's like it's all torn, and therefore it is
טהור. tahor. Okay, yes.
A טלית talit that's torn is טמא?
tamei No, it became טמא tamei, and you are tearing it and
thereby making it no longer טלית talit to make it now טהור.
tahor Okay. By the way, טלית talit here does not mean a
thing with ציצית tzitzit on it. It just means an outer garment.
Okay. Now, וטהורה. u-tehorah. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה, לא שנו אלא בטלית טבולת יום. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, lo shanu ela be-talit tevulat yom. It's only if you
first brought it to the מקווה mikvah, that day, okay? Which you
could just now wait till evening, but you were so eager to
make it טהור tahor. that you tore it already before evening. You
changed your mind. You were very, you got so eager. You first
took it to the מקווה, mikvah. "Wait, I need it right now."
Okay, anyway, somehow you need cloth, not your טלית, talit, obviously. Okay.
דלא חס עלה ואטבלה, De-lo chas lah ve-atvlah, since you did not
care for its survival, the proof is that you dunked it in
a מקווה. mikvah Taking a nice cloth טלית talit and dunking it
in a מקווה mikvah. is going to get it hard and ruined
or whatever. You know, I mean, it's like, you know, imagine a,
you know, dry cleaning only, no, you know, do not whatever, and
you went and you put it in a מקווה. mikvah, So clearly
you don't care about it. So since you don't care about it,
you're just trying to get the cloth out of this. לא חייס
עלה וקרע לה רובה. Lo chayeis lah ve-kara lah rubah. Then when
you tear it, you're not going to try to preserve it and
you'll tear the majority. אבל טלית שאינה טבולת יום, Aval talit she-einah
tevulat yom, if you didn't dunk it into the מקווה, mikvah no.
Tearing it the majority does not make it טהור. tahor Why? Rabbinically.
גזירה דילמא לא אתי למקרע רובה, Gezeirah dilma lo ati lemikra rubah,
because you're going to be so concerned, you're going to want to
sew it up afterwards. You're not going to want to tear, if
you're just tearing it, you're making it טהור tahor, and now you're
going to want to sew it up again. I don't know, you
know, so why, and you didn't take it to the מקווה because
that would ruin it more than a tear and a sewing up.
Okay? So, in that type of a case, maybe you tore it
at the back where nobody's going to see it. Anyway, in that
case we're afraid you're so much trying to preserve it that you're
going to not do the majority. You'll do half, you'll do forty
percent, you'll convince yourself you've done the majority when you haven't yet
done the majority. So in that case we're going to force you
to tear the whole thing because we're not going to trust you
to just do the majority, to get as far as the majority.
Yes.
So is this where the logic comes in to why you can't
repair the torn קריעה? kriah?
No. That has to do with an act of אָבֵל. avel. Okay
now אמר רבא שתי תשובות בדבר *Amar Rava, shtei teshuvos badavar*. רבא
*Rava* does not like this qualification. Two responses. Number one, חדא *chada*,
שמא יאמרו טבילה בת יומא עולה *shema yomru tvila bas yoma ola*.
You're concerned about a גזרה *gzaira* that he might not tear the
opposite instead of majority. I'll give you another... I'll counter your גזרה
*gzaira* with another גזרה *gzaira*. If the guy did it in the
מקוה *mikvah* and then tore it and now he's using it in
a טהור tahor, *tahor* context, people will have seen that he took
it in the מקוה *mikvah* and normally you take it in the
מקוה *mikvah* you only tear that night. People will see he took
it to the מקוה *mikvah* and he's using it that day or
the cloth of it. They won't realize that he tore it or
they won't realize they'll associate the fact that he's treating it as
טהור tahor *tahor* with the fact that it went to the מקוה
*mikvah* even though he didn't wait till the next night. So I
have an equal concern in your case, I'll make another גזרה *gzaira*.
Your case about going to the מקוה *mikvah*. People will think that
you don't have to wait till the night. They'll see him take
it to the מקוה *mikvah* and they'll see him use it on
the same day. Better not to have taken it to the מקוה
*mikvah* all together and then they'll understand that it was because it
was torn, which is why it was being used.
Oh, so that's answer number one. And in terms of your concern
that he's not going to get around to doing the majority, here's
what I have to say in response: עולת העוף לרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון ליגזר דילמא לא אתי למעבד רוב שנים *Olas ha'of l'Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon l'gzar dilma lo asi l'ma'avid rov shnayim*. So when you
were back to קדשים kodshim. *Kodshim*, when you שחט *shacht* a bird
עולה *olah*, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon* says that
you are not allowed, although you have to cut the majority of
both סימנים *simanim*, you are not allowed to sever the entire head.
So he says, well, if your concern is that when somebody has
to do a majority they won't come to do the majority they'll
only do halfway, okay, why according to him do we say just
do the majority, don't sever the head? Shouldn't we be concerned that
if he tries to be careful, you know, if he just tries
to do the majority and not sever the head, he won't even,
if he tries to be careful about not severing the head, he
won't even do the majority, he'll only do 50%? So obviously we
are not concerned, we can trust people to do the right amount.
Okay, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says that the question might not be exactly
that we should require him to do it completely, but at least
we should require him to do like a רוב הניכר rov hanikar,
*rov hanikar*. We shouldn't say 51%. We should say do 70%. Nobody's
going to confuse 49% with
70%. And that's the question here too. Why do we say it's
enough to do just the majority of two?
Why why shouldn't we say you should do a רוב הניכר *rov
hanikar*? Obviously we're not concerned that people will make that mistake. אמר
ליה רב יוסף *Amar lei Rav Yosef*... what?
שחיטה *shechita* now is רוב הניכר *rov hanikar*.
Okay, there you go. That's a good... that's a good point. Okay,
so אמר ליה רב יוסף *Amar lei Rav Yosef* says that you
know that by when Mordechai says when we do שחיטה *shechita*, even
though technically 51% is enough, you tell people to do it as
a very obvious רוב *rov*, you know, whatever that is, 70%. You
don't want people making mistakes between 49% and 51%. So anyway, אמר
ליה רב יוסף *Amar lei Rav Yosef*. So now here's the response
back to support the idea that we do try to, you know,
we don't like people to rely on majority
and we're going to limit the case to only having taken it
to the מקוה *mikvah* that day. דאמרת גזרה שמא יאמרו טבילה בת
יומא עולה *D'amarta gzaira shema yomru tvila bas yoma ola*. Your concern
that if you took it to the מקוה *mikvah* that day and
there we allow 51%, people will think that the טבילה *tvila* worked
without waiting till the night. No, קרע מוכיח עליה *kra mochiach aleha*.
People see that it's torn. Although they saw you took it to
the מקוה *mikvah*, they'll also see that it's torn and they're not
going to get confused that it was the מקוה *mikvah* that made
it טהור tahor *tahor*. Which I don't know, that גזרה *gzaira* seemed
to make a lot of sense. Anyway, number one. ודאמרת עולת העוף
לרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון ליגזר *V'damarta olas ha'of l'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
lygzar*. Why by the bird עולה *olah* do we say don't do
the whole thing? Why maybe we should דוקא *davka* say do the
whole thing in order to make sure that you don't stop at
49% or something, or 50% without doing 51%? כהנים זריזים הם *Kohanim
zrizim heim*. כהנים *Kohanim* are very punctilious and careful and they can
do... they'll do the majority and be very careful to make sure
they get the majority and they'll also at the same time be
careful to stop before they do the whole thing. So basically we're
back to the question of when do we trust somebody when they
say the majority makes it okay that they're not going to try
to be protective of the thing or, you know, and not do
the full job and do only 49% and not do 51%? Or
are we going to demand that they do either רוב הניכר *rov
hanikar* or do the whole thing? That's the question. Okay, so we're
going to try to figure that out now and we're going to...
this is how we double back to our case. תא שמע ta
shema, *Ta shma* come and hear: המפשיט בבהמה ובחיה בטמאה ובטהורה בדקה
ובגסה *Hamafshit b'behema u'vchaya b'tmeia u'vtahora b'daka u'vgasa*. Our משנה Mishnah, *mishna*
that you're flaying the skin off of any type of an animal.
וכשיעור כדי אחיזה kedei achiza *U'keshiur k'dei achiza*. When if it's for
the sake of a mat then the כדי אחיזה kedei achiza. *k'dei
achiza*, which is two טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* right by the skin, is
still considered connected. היתר מכדי אחיזה טהור tahor *Hayaser mik'dei achiza tahor*.
It means as soon as you get beyond that amount, if you
touch the flap of the leather, it doesn't communicate to טומאה tumah.
*tumah*. So if you're so concerned, basically it's a general question, right,
about every time that there's a שיעור shiur *shiur*, should we always
make a safeguard, you know, should we always make like a בין
השמשות *bein hashmashos* to every שיעור *shiur*, right, should we always add
like a חזון איש *Chazon Ish* amount to every שיעור *shiur* just
in order that you don't make a distinction between are you over
the line or not over the line? So it says now here
it seems to be that it's raised... raising the question in the
context of, although it states it in כל התורה כולה, but here
it seems to be raising it in the context in the case
of where you're tearing things or pulling things apart is sort of
what brings specifically looking at these cases together. So here, why don't
we say that if we tell you that once you get beyond
that first two טפחים, tefachim the flap doesn't communicate טומאה, tumah that
you're not going to do the whole thing and you'll confuse the
case of when it's less than כדי אחיזה kedei achiza? and more
than כדי אחיזה. kedei achiza, Why aren't we concerned? Okay now of
course it's a little bit different. In one case you're tearing the
טלית tallis with the purpose of making it טהור, tahor it sounds
like it, at least that could be the case. Here you're just
trying to flay. The fact that something טמא tamei touched the skin
was completely incidental and random. But anyway that's the גמרא'ס gemara's question.
Okay, why do we allow it to be exactly כדי אחיזה? kedei
achiza, Why aren't we concerned that you'll make a mistake?
אמאי, amai, why is that true? לגזור דלמא אתי למעבד אלא כדי
אחיזה, ligzor dilma asi lemevad ela kedei achiza, you'll only do exactly
the כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza? you won't do more than that. You
in your mind will think that you've done, you've pulled away enough
and it's not a problem, ותיגע בטומאה, vesiga betumah, it'll touch something
טמא, tamei. וקמתהרינן ליה, vekamitahrinan lei, and you'll say everything is טהור,
tahor right? And how would you allow somebody to rely on that
and not demand that they do more than the שיעור and pull
it away even more? Because shouldn't we be making a safeguard? So
the גמרא gemara says, אי בטומאה דאורייתא הכי נמי, ei betumah deoraisa
hachi nami, if we were talking about biblical טומאה, tumah, you'd be
right, we wouldn't allow it to be just a כדי אחיזה, kedei
achiza, we'd have to make a safeguard. הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai
askinan, what are we talking about? בטומאה דרבנן, betumah derabbanan, it's a
rabbinic טומאה, tumah. something rabbinically טמא tamei, touches the skin and the
question is does it make the meat טמא. tamei Now that works
when you're... the question is making the meat טמא, tamei? you could
have something rabbinically טמא tamei touch the skin. But the other case
is that the meat is a נבלה, neveila, that's biblical, and you're
touching the skin and do you become טמא? tamei So that's a
biblical issue. So again, why don't we make a safeguard? So the
גמרא gemara says, תינח, teinach, what,
as this practically seems like a moot point though because you're the
one beginning the flaying process and for sure at the outset you're
in contact.
That's true, it would have to be some other person, some third
party touched it. You're right, that's a good point. So the גמרא
gemara says, תינח טמא בטהור, teinach tamei betahor, that works, that if
something טמא tamei. touched טהור tahor, meat, that the thing that was
טהור tahor? or the skin of the טהור tahor meat, that the
thing that was טמא tamei. could have been rabbinically
טמא. tamei. טהור בטמא, tahor betamei, טומאה דאורייתא היא, tumah deoraisa hi,
but if you're a טהור tahor, person, not the guy doing the
flay as Mordechai points out, a טהור tahor, person touching the skin
and the animal itself is a נבלה neveila or it's a pig
which by definition is a נבלה, neveila, right, anyway then that's a
biblical טומאה. tumah. So if you think that when you're pulling things
you have to do extra to be safe, why don't we demand
more than the amount of כדי אחיזה? kedei achiza So the גמרא
gemara says
בטרפה, bitreifa, no, we're not talking about pig and we're not talking
about נבלה. neveila. When the משנה Mishnah talks about the fact that
the animal is טמאה, it does not mean a non-kosher species, pig,
and it does not mean a נבלה, neveila, it means that it's
a טרפה. treifa. And there is an idea of rabbinic טומאה tumah
by a טרפה. treifa. Really biblically you shecht a טרפה treifa it's
טהור, tahor, but there's a rabbinic טומאה, tumah, and therefore we are
talking only within the world of rabbinic טומאה. tumah So the גמרא
gemara doesn't believe that there's a rabbinic טומאה. tumah, טרפה בת טומאה
היא? treifa bas tumah hi? Is a טרפה treifa have any טומאה
tumah. even rabbinic טומאה, tumah, isn't a טרפה treifa supposed to be
טהור? tahor. So the גמרא gemara says, אין, in, yes, כדאבוה דשמואל,
kedavuh deshmual, like the
father of שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר אבוה דשמואל, damar avuh deshmual, טרפה ששחטה,
treifa sheshachta, מטמא במוקדשין, metamei bemukdashin, that even when you shecht a
טרפה, treifa, although it's טהור tahor biblically and rabbinically, there is a
rabbinic
טומאה tumah vis-a-vis קדשים. kodshim If it touches קדשים kodshim, or touches
you and then you want to eat קדשים, kodshim for קדשים purposes
we consider a טרפה treifa still to be טמא. tamei So basically,
although the simple sense of this משנה Mishnah is undoubtedly with biblical
טומאה, tumah we have this question about why are we, why do
we trust you כדי אחיזה, kedei achiza why don't we demand that
you pull away more? As you say that generally we would demand
people do more than just the minimum amount. And the answer is
somehow make it that it's all talking about just rabbinic טומאה. tumah,
Okay, תא
שמע, we're not done yet with this case.
רב דוסטאי בן יהודה משום רבי שמעון אומר, Rav Dustai ben Yehuda
mishum Rabi Shimon omer, so רב דוסטאי Rav Dustai in the name
of רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon says, המפשיט בשרצים, hamapshit beshretzim, you are
now flaying שרצים, shretzim, like you're flaying mice. You want mouse skin.
Okay. חיבור עד שיפשיט את כולו. chibbur ad sheyapshit es kulo. So
that is considered connected until you completely remove it. I suppose presumably
the skin is very closely connected, so until you actually flay away
all of it, or maybe there's not even two טפחים worth of
skin to begin with, anyway it's all considered connected.
Could be just like reptiles, right? Could be...
oh that's a good... that's a good example. Alligator skin. That's a
good example. What? Okay, that's a good example, yeah.
Okay, so the גמרא gemara says, הא בגמל, אינו חיבור. Ha begamal
eino chibur, So that suggests because again our question is, like the
טלית, tallis, why do we allow... I sort of introduced תוספות Tosafot
that said רוב הניכר, but the simple sense of this גמרא Gemara
is why don't we demand all? So by the טלית tallis do
you allow allow a majority or are you going to demand him
to demand that he completely tear the טלית? tallis? In our משנה
Mishnah. why do you allow after כדי אחיזה to be okay? Why
don't you demand that the entire skin be removed? That's the question.
And we tried to say we're talking about a rabbinic case. So
here we are talking about here we say that again, if you
have a שרץ sheretz all, so it sounds like if it was
a non-kosher animal that wasn't a שרץ, sheretz, like a camel, you
wouldn't have to remove all of it. Now why is that, why
do we bring that, why is that more powerful than our משנה?
Mishnah. Because since we're talking about שרצים, sheratzim, we're talking about things
that cause טומאה, tumah right? A שרץ sheretz causes טומאה tumah if
it's one of the eight שרצים. sheratzim. So the analogous case is
a camel which also causes biblical טומאה tumah because of a נבילה,
neveilah, and so you can't give me some answer we're only dealing
with rabbinic טומאה, tumah right? The analogous case is a camel which
is biblical טומאה tumah. as a נבילה, neveilah, and there the implication
is you don't have to remove all of it, only some lesser
amount, כדי אחיזה would be enough. So you see even when you're
dealing with biblical טומאה we do not demand that you completely tear
the thing away. So the גמרא Gemara says, doesn't that suggest by
a camel you don't have to remove all of it?
הא בגמל אינו חיבור, ha begamal eino chibur I'm sorry, the גמרא
Gemara says לא תימא lo teima no, don't say הא בגמל ha
begamal, אינו חיבור eino chibbur. by a camel it's not
connected, it less than all of it is not connected. That's not
true. By a camel you would have to remove all of it
and anything less would be considered connected. אלא אימא Ella eima בעור
של הצואר be'or shel hatzavar אינו חיבור. eino chibur. The issue is,
is the question about the neck skin, meaning it could be that
by the time you get like we taught in our משנה, Mishnah
right, by the time you get to the neck you don't have
to remove all of it, so because then it's considered that it'll
all easily fall off. So as opposed to the case by the
שרצים, sheratzim, by שרצים sheratzim even presumably the neck area you would
have to literally remove. So it says by שרץ sheretz you have
to remove all of it, which means by other things not all,
but not all could still mean all except for the neck. Okay,
which is essentially all. So the גמרא Gemara is still resisting obviously
the simple point about all these משניות Mishnayot and all these ברייתות,
braitot, which is you can have less than even when you've just
removed a טפח tefach or two or certainly less than all, it's
no longer considered connected. It wants to assert that we would normally
make a גזירה gezeirah and all the cases where it would say
less than all is not considered connected would either be rabbinic טומאה
or that you've done everything but the neck. But anything beyond that
would still be considered connected and we would make a גזירה gezeirah
lest you come not to do enough.
Okay, yes, we're saying if once all of it's removed it's טהור,
tahor right? Yes, the skin, the skin. So then what's the situation
about having to walk on it for 72 minutes?
Oh, that was by skins that are considered like flesh, like by
let's say chicken skins. Here we're talking about like cow skins which
are considered distinct from the flesh. It's thicker skin. The thicker skin,
yeah, exactly. All right, so okay, so okay, רבי יוחנן בן נורי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri here, and it's רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri in our משנה, Mishnah. right, because in our משנה
Mishnah what does רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri say
that
that once you get to the neck it's no longer connected. So
the גמרא Gemara is trying to say that when it comes to
טומאה טהרה tumah taharah and if something's considered connected or not, maybe
we should make a גזירה gezeirah and never consider it connected until
you've completely removed it. And maybe the only time we'll make an
exception is well okay maybe the neck part you don't have to
remove if you've removed everything else, or by rabbinic טומאה maybe that's
what our משנה Mishnah is talking about, you can remove less. But
in general it's trying to say for טומאה טהרה tumah taharah you
would have to remove it completely like you'd have to tear the
טלית tallis completely. Again, not at all the simple sense of the
משנה. Let's keep on going. Okay,
where were we? אמר רב הונא משום רבי שמעון בר יוסי, Amar
Rav Huna mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yossi, לא שנו, lo shanu, now
we're so we've had that debate whether to take the case of
טלית tallis literally about majority or not. But now we go back
to the case of the טלית. tallis. לא שנו, when is this
true that tearing the majority of the טלית tallis works, אלא assuming
that we don't make this גזירה gezeirah we've been talking about, אלא
שלא שייר בה כדי מעפורת. ella shelo shiyer bah kedei ma'aforet. You
did not leave at the bottom of the טלית tallis enough to
be used as a type of a cloth or a handkerchief. אבל
שייר בה כדי מעפורת, Aval shiyer bah kedei ma'aforet,
if you did leave enough to like a wrap maybe is a
better translation of a מעפורת, ma'aforet, if you didn't leave enough to
serve as a wrap, חיבור chibur it's connected. Now that again is
against the simple, certainly against the simple sense of the משנה. The
משנה says majority, but he's saying, so first we had one approach,
it's funny how many people are like anxious to qualify this משנה.
Once you tear the טלית tallis majority it works. Oh wait we
should make a גזירה gezeirah and say normally that doesn't work you
have to do the whole thing. And then the גמרא Gemara thought
based on our משנה it doesn't sound like you make גזירות gezeirot
when about that type of stuff. That was one issue. Let's put
the גזירה gezeirah aside. Yes, forget גזירה, gezeirah, majority. Now the next
qualification is oh but that's only if including the majority there's not
like a good amount of cloth at the bottom that can be
used as a type of a wrap. But if let's say you
tore the majority of the of the jacket but there's
still
30%...
What? If he's doing majority or 60%, you're always going to have
a significant...
Well, not if the whole בגד beged is small. If the whole
בגד beged is small and you do 51%, maybe there's not enough
underneath to be used for anything good. But if it's a big
בגד, beged, it'll almost always... תוספות Tosafot quotes a גמרא Gemara that
says this is only rabbinic, which makes sense. The משנה is talking
biblically. Biblically, once you tear the majority, it's considered no longer a
טלית, tallis, it's טהור, tahor but maybe rabbinically, if there's enough cloth
to be used at the bottom, it's still considered connected and still
טמא. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish said, now ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish has a different qualification. לא שנו אלא טלית. Lo shanu
ela tallis. When do we say majority makes it considered no longer
a טלית? tallis? That's by cloth. אבל עור, Aval or, if it's
a leather garment, חלים, cholim, then that can... then that's strong and
that can be... that can be fixed better. Now, I don't know
about you, you know, it would seem to me that... that sewing
a cloth garment is, you know, it doesn't look as bad than
if you had a tear in a leather garment and you had
to sew it up. But we're not just talking about how bad
it will look when you sew it up, but also when if
you've done the tearing, how much easier is it going to be
that it's now going to... it's almost about to completely tear, like
the tear's going to naturally finish by itself. Okay, so we want
to say basically conceptually when you tore the majority of the טלית,
tallis, what we're saying is it's like the whole טלית tallis is
in two pieces. That's the whole point. אין חיבור. Ein chibur. It's
not like it's one piece anymore, it's not like it's a טלית.
tallis. So you can say that by cloth, which if you've torn
the majority, it's going to... naturally the rest will tear very easily.
But by leather, even if you've torn the majority, the rest won't
necessarily tear as easily. I don't know. Is that consistent with people's
experience?
It's not woven.
Well, so I understand, right. So...
I
know, but that's the point. We're not talking about sewing, we're talking
more about the... how easily will the remainder tear? And therefore, the
fact that there is a remainder is still enough to consider it
to be one piece and it would still retain its טומאה. Okay.
רש"י Rashi says, meaning, I mentioned the sewing because that's what רש"י
Rashi says. רש"י Rashi says by leather when you sew it up,
it'll retain its integrity more than when you sew up a cloth
garment. But to me, that's very hard to understand.
To me, it seems to make more sense to say that by
a cloth garment when you tear the majority, the remainder will tear
easily, whereas by leather not necessarily. But רש"י Rashi speaks about... if
we're trying to see it as one garment, by a cloth garment
once you sew it up, it won't so much retain its integrity,
leather more... more will. But I don't know, that doesn't seem to
make sense to me. What? I guess you can patch leather. I
don't know. Anyway.
Okay. Oh my gosh, I just looked at the time. Okay, so
he says it would not be the same by leather. So let's
just read two more lines here. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש
לקיש. Ativ lei Rabbi Yochanan le-Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about his whole leather... רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi
Yochanan amar, excuse me, אפילו עור נמי לא חלים. afilu or nami
lo cholim. Even leather is not strong and therefore has the same
rule as cloth. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, Ativ lei Rabbi Yochanan
le-Reish Lakish, he asked ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. עור טמא מדרס. Or
tamei midras. So if you have this leather that is טמא because
a זב zav sat on it, it was serving as a type
of a mat.
חישב עליו לרצועות וסנדלים. Chishav alav lirtzuot vesandalim. You're saying, okay, you
know what I'm going to do? I'm going to make strips of
that and use it to make a sandal or to make leather
strips, I don't know, to make a belt.
Okay. כיון שנתן בו איזמל, Keivan shenatan bo izmel, as soon as
you began to do it, you placed your awl to the leather,
even before you've actually really cut it, but now you're in the
process of transforming it, טהור, tahor. you've changed its status. דברי רבי
יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda, which is much more radical than we said
so far. וחכמים veChachamim אומרים, omrim the sages say, עד שימעיטנו מחמשה
טפחים. ad sheyamitenu mechamesh tefachim. No, until you actually cut it and
there's less than חמישה טפחים chamisha tefachim left, only then is it
טהור. And now תוספות says the less than חמישה טפחים chamisha tefachim
by leather is the same as a less than a majority by
the cloth. Okay, but even so, the point is is that there
is... once you go beyond a certain size, it's now considered destroyed.
Is this דאורייתא? de-oraita? Yes. Is this דרבנן? de-rabbanan? No.
No, no, it's different for each garment. So for a cloth, it's
considered טהור when less than a majority is left or less than
half is left. By leather, it's considered טהור when less than חמישה
טפחים. chamisha tefachim. But nevertheless, the point is that by leather, there
is a minimum amount that becomes טהור and we don't say that
you'll just patch it up. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, כי
ממעיט ליה מחמשה טפחים, ki mamit lei mi-hamesh tefachim, when you get
beyond חמישה טפחים chamisha tefachim it's טהור. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says, how do you explain that ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? You're saying
that leather somehow is stronger and these things aren't a problem with
leather. So אמאי, amai, why is that? לימא חלים, Leima cholim, say
it's strong. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. כי אמרי דחלים, Ki
amri de-cholim, when do I say leather is strong? היכא דקצריה ליה
להדיא, Heicha de-katzrei lei le-hedya, when you cut it straight, meaning it's
like a, you know, a linear cut. הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha de-mai
askinan, what are we talking about here? במקצעה ובא לו דרך סביבותיו.
bi-mekatze'o u-valo derech sevivatav. That what you're doing is you're like cutting...
cutting all around, cutting out squares, you know, you're cutting things. So
if you do a straight cut down, you can just like sew
it up and it's strong and so on and maybe, you know,
it still retains its integrity. But if you're cutting first a strip
lengthwise and widthwise and this, etcetera, you know, then there's no way
that you're going to somehow repair it and get it back to
its original state. Okay, so we'll end here with this question about
at what stage when you tear things do they retain their integrity,
and the analogy to us is, you know, you're tearing the skin
off of the the skin off of the meat, to what degree
is it still connected? Not exactly the same point, one is if
the garment, the object retains its integrity, the other is, is it
connected to the meat below, but there's a certain analogy and with
this the גמרא will continue tomorrow.
Just one off.
Okay, that's fine, you can get the